Guide to the Francis William Bourdillon Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Francis William Bourdillon collection
1874-1921
1880-1900
OSB MSS 165
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.83
(4 boxes)
The collection consists almost entirely of printed copies of works by Francis William Bourdillon, especially his narrative poems and occasional verse, along with several versions of his translation of Aucassin et Nicolette. In addition, there are sketchbooks, etchings, and a photograph album containing views of the Swiss Alps.
Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from John Hart on the Hazel M. Osborn Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Francis William Bourdillon (1852-1921)
Francis William Bourdillon was born in Buddington, Sussex and educated at Worcester College, Oxford. He served as tutor to the sons of Prince Christian of Schleswig-Holstein at Cumberland Lodge for several years. He later tutored for the University of Eastbourne, and settled in Eastbourne, Sussex.
Bourdillon published thirteen collections of poetry between 1874 and 1921, as well as single poems and narrative verses, many of them privately printed in limited editions. He is best-known today for the short poem "Light" ('The night has a thousand eyes.") Among his other publications were scholarly editions and translations of Old French literature; his translation of Aucassin et Nicolette appeared in 1887 and was a popular success.
In addition, Bourdillion was a member of the Alpine Club and campaigned for the preservation of the Alps against excessive development. He died in Eastbourne in 1921.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists almost entirely of printed copies of works by Francis William Bourdillon, especially his poems and occasional verse, along with several versions of his translation of Aucassin et Nicolette. In addition, there are sketchbooks, etchings, and a photograph album containing views of the Swiss Alps.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Verse and Other Publications, 1874-1921. II. Aucassin et Nicolette and Related French Romance Publications, 1880-1917. III. Other Papers, 1882-1917. IV. Oversize Material, 1880-1919.
Aucassin et Nicolette -- Translations; Authors, English -- 19th century; English poetry -- 19th century; English poetry -- 20th Century; French poetry -- To 1500 -- Translations into English; Occasional verse, English; Alps, Swiss (Switzerland) -- Pictorial works; Photograph albums; Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921
- Verse and Other Publications, 1874-1921; Series I; 1; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Verse and Other Publications. Verse is chronologically arranged, and Other Publications is in no particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains copies of poems by Bourdillon, chronologically arranged by date of publication, and other publications. Many of these items were privately printed or very limited editions.
  Notes below some folder titles are references to A Bookman's Catalogue: The Norman Colbeck Collection of Nineteenth-Century and Edwardian Poetry and Belles Lettres in the Special Collections of the University of British Columbia .Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1987. Additional bibliographic information on many items can be found in the dealer list, Box 1, folder 1.
  - Verse
    - Dealer list, undated (Box 1)
    - Gertrude's Love: A Legend of Gloucester Hall, 1874 (Box 1)
      Not in Colbeck.
    - Two Songs Sung at F.S. Gibbons' Farewell Supper, June 4th, 1875 (Box 1)
      No copy recorded.
    - In Memoriam. Darmstadt. December 14th, 1878, 1879 (Box 1)
    - Morn in Mid-April, [circa 1880?] (Box 1)
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, [circa1887] (Box 1)
    - Light, [circa 1890?] (Box 1)
    - Love Lies Bleeding, 1891 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.8.
    - Love Lies Bleeding, 1891 (Box 1)
    - A Lost God. With Illustrations by H.J. Ford, 1891 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.6.
    - A Lost God. With Illustrations by H.J. Ford, 1891 (Box 1)
    - Love in a Mist, 1892 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.10.
    - Sursum Corda, 1893 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.11.
    - Chryseis, 1894 (Box 1)
    - Minuscula. Lyrics of Nature, Art and Love, 1897 (Box 1)
    - To the Dear Memory of H.H. Prince Christian Victor of Schleswig-Holstein, 1900 November (Box 1)
    - Ailes d'Alouette. (Second Series), 1902 (Box 1)
    - In Memoriam. The Late John Heywood Johnstone, Esq, MP. of Bignor Park, Sussex and Trewithen, Cornwall, 1904 (Box 1)
    - Quia Agnosco, Credo, 1907 (Box 1)
    - Preludes and Romances, 1908 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.20.
    - Verses by V, 1910 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.2.
    - In Praise of Sussex: An Ode Written for the Ceremonial Opening of the Chichester High School for Girls, October 27th, 1910 (Box 1)
    - In Praise of Sussex. Written for the Inaguration of Foundation Day. Chichester HIgh School for Girls. June 10th. 1911 (Box 1)
    - In Memoriam H.A.L. [Lieutenant-Colonel H.A.Lascelles], 1913 July (Box 1)
    - A Prayer of Nations during World War. Words and Music, [circa 1915?] (Box 1)
    - Easter Lilies for Nineteen Hundred and Fifteen, [1915] (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.23.
    - Russia Re-Born, 1917 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 82.24.
    - A Hymn of Hope, [circa 1919] (Box 1)
    - A Hymn of Hope, [circa 1919] (Box 1)
    - Gerard & Isabel. A Romance in Form of Cantefable, 1921 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 82.25.
  - Other Publications
    - "Beachy Head," A Paper Read before the Eastbourne Natural History Society, [1894?] (Box 1)
    - Nephele, 1896 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.13.
    - Nephele: A Musical Romance, 1899 (Box 1)
      See Colbeck 81.13 for the English edition published in 1896.
    - The Smithereens: A Drawing-Room Farce in Three Scenes, 1898 (Box 1)
      Colbeck 81.15. Not in NUC or the British Library Catalogue.
    - The Smithereens: A Drawing-Room Farce in Three Scenes, [1898] (Box 1)
    - [Theatre Programme]. The Smithereens, a Drawing-Room Farce, in Three Scenes, [1898] (Box 1)
- Aucassin et Nicolette and Related French Romance Publications, 1887-1920; Series II; 1; (1 box)
  Versions of Aucassin & Nicolette, chronologically arranged, are followed by chronologically arranged works related to other French romances.
  The series contains several editions of Bourdillon's popular translation of Aucassin & Nicolette, as well as printed items connected with his work on other French romances.
  - Aucassin & Nicolette
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, a Love Story: Edited in Old French and Rendered in Modern English, 1887 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, A Love Story: Edited in Old French and Rendered in Modern English, 1887 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, A Love Story: Edited in Old French, and Rendered in Modern English, (With Introduction, Glossary, Etc.), 1887 (Box 2)
      Colbeck 80.3.
    - C'est Daucasi & De Nicolette, 1896 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, 1897 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin & Nicolette, 1897 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin and Nicolette. Translated from the Old French, 1903 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin and Nicolette. Translated from the Old French, 1903 (Box 2)
    - Aucassin and Nicolette. Illustrated by Katharine Cameron, [1908] (Box 2)
    - Aucassin et Nicolette. Edited by F.W. Bourdillon., 1919 (Box 2)
  - Related French Romance Publications
    - Tote Listoire De France (Chronique Saintongeaise). Now First Edited From the Only Two Mss., With Introduction, Appendices, and Notes. With Prefatory Letter by Gaston Paris, 1897 (Box 2)
    - The Genesis of a Romance-Hero, as Illustrated by the Development of Taillefer de Leon, 1896 September (Box 2)
    - Bibliographical Society. Table and Facsimiles to Illustrate Mr. Bourdillon's Paper on Early Editions of the Roman de la Rose, 1904 February 15 (Box 2)
    - A Verard Fragment of the Roman de la Rose, 1913 July (Box 2)
    - Theseus de Cologne: Notes on a Fragment of a Lost Edition, and an Unknown Version of the Romance, 1918 (Box 2)
    - Bibliographical Society. Facsimiles of Woodcuts to Illustrate Mr. Bourdillon's Paper: Notes on Some French Romances, 1919 December 15 (Box 2)
    - Some Notes on Two Early Romances. Huon de Bordeaux and Melusine, 1920 (Box 2)
- Other Papers, 1882-1917; Series III; 11
  Unarranged.
  The series contains three sketchbooks, seven etchings, and several folders of printed material related to Bourdillon.
  - Three pocket sketchbooks, undated (Box 2)
  - Seven loose etchings of Bourdillon's drawings, undated (Box 2)
  - A Border Ballad. Words by F.W.Bourdillon. Music by Oliveria Prescott, 1882 April 1 (Box 2)
  - Tunes of a Rhymer, 1914 (Box 2)
  - Five printed settings of Different Poems by Bourdillon, undated (Box 2)
  - 'Without are Dogs.' Reprinted from the 'Alpine Journal', May 1913 (Box 2)
  - Gait and Style. Reprinted from 'The Alpine Journal,' February 1917 (Box 2)
  - The Accidents on the Wetterhorn, 1902 November (Box 2)
- Oversize Material, 1880-1919; Series IV; 1.83; (2 boxes)
  The series consists of several oversize printed items and an album containing photographs of landscapes in the Swiss Alps and of several mansions in Sussex.
  - Aucassin et Nicolette, [circa 1887?] (Box 3)
  - The Night Has a Thousand Eyes. [Light], undated (Box 3)
  - Return. Song, Words by Robert Bridges, Music by F.W.B., undated (Box 3)
  - Sweet Primroses. Words by F.W. Bourdillon. Music by Louise Dickes, undated (Box 3)
  - TLS from Arthur Humphreys on Hatchards' notepaper to Bourdillon, 1919 (Box 3)
  - Photograph album, [circa 1880-1900] (Box 4)